<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Epaphras, A sermon preached at Saint Austell in Cornwal, in commemoration of a benefactor, the second of February, 1639 by Ioseph May ...</title>
            <author>May, Joseph, b. 1584 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13144067</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13144067</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98029</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50354)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98029)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 428:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Epaphras, A sermon preached at Saint Austell in Cornwal, in commemoration of a benefactor, the second of February, 1639 by Ioseph May ...</title>
                  <author>May, Joseph, b. 1584 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 28, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.H. for Humphrey Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, May 29, 1641. Johannes Hansley"--P. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians IV, 12-13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98029:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98029:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Epaphras. A SERMON PREACHED AT SAINT <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STELL</hi> IN CORNWAL: IN COMMEMORATION of a Benefactor, the ſecond of <hi>February,</hi> 1639.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Ioſeph May, <hi>Maſter of Arts, and Paſtour of that Pariſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 13.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>To doe good, and to diſtribute forget not; for with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. H.</hi> for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the three Pigeons in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epistle_dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98029:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98029:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS WORTHY FRIEND, AND FRIENDLY Benefactor, Mr. <hi>Richard Delamaine,</hi> ſervant to his Majeſty in the practice of the Mathematickes.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His new borne Babe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth admittance into your boſome, and that juſtly, becauſe it is one of your own begetting: your Purſe and my Pen have joyned for the production of this Iſſue; which now (as you ſee) hath taken foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſtep abroad into the world. I for my part have deſigned it for the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, there to hold a candle, that ſome dim-ſighted-paſſengers might by its light finde out a way to the poor mans Box; and that by the ſame light I and my
<pb facs="tcp:98029:3"/>fellow ſervants may behold what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of man <hi>Epaphras</hi> was, for our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and imitation. I have ſent it unto you without Bag or Scrip, very naked, yet in ſuch garments as <hi>Truth</hi> uſeth to put on. You that love your Countrey ſo well, cannot chuſe but make much of your owne childe, borne in your owne Pariſh, and one that doth ſo well reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you. I have onely taught him his prayers, or rather I have learned from him how to pray; eſpecially for you, that you may ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God: Which duty ſhall alwayes be really performed by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours truely obliged, <hi>JOSEPH MAY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98029:3"/>
            <head>To his beloved Pariſhioners of Saint AUSTEL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved Friends and Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners, it was for your ſakes that I preached this Sermon, and you know by whoſe procurement: They are ſalutations which I preſented unto you from a friend of yours, wherein you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his love and zealous affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this place, the place of his birth and firſt breeding. It is my deſire that among the many Sermons which I have delivered, ſome one may be more powerfull then the reſt, to worke in you an imitation of our Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors good workes (the glory of God being his chiefe aime) and that it bee not raked in oblivion, or as a Candle put under a Buſhell, when it was intended to give light to the
<pb facs="tcp:98029:4"/>whole houſe. I have here publiſhed what I formerly preached; you have the light both of the word of God, and the good workes of men, walke in the light of the one, by the light of the other, that yee may be the children of light, and ſo at length placed in glory (like ſtarres in the firmament) with him who one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath immortality, and dwelleth in that light which no man can approach unto: whereunto tendeth the labour and ſervice of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your friend and Miniſter, JOSEPH MAY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98029:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Col. 4.12, 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epaphras,</hi> who is one of you, a ſervant of Chriſt ſaluteth you, alwayes labouring fervently for you in prayers; that yee may ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God; For I beare him record that he hath a great zeale for you, and them that are at <hi>Laodicea,</hi> and them in <hi>Hierapolis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Saints and faithfull bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren which were at <hi>Coloſſe</hi> a city of Greece, conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the faith of Jeſus Chriſt, by the faithfull miniſtry of <hi>Epaphras,</hi> give occaſion to our Apoſtle to rejoyce, be holding their order and ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſle of faith in Chriſt upon the heare-ſay and report that came to him,<note place="margin">Col. 2.5.</note> and therefore made them a choice part of his Apoſtolicall charge, whereby to animate,<note place="margin">Col. 2.1.</note> and confirme them in the faith received: And however he had not ſeen them in the fleſh yet his ſpirit and heart went with them; and this Epiſtle is ſent unto them by <hi>Tychicus</hi> a faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,<note place="margin">Col. 4.7, 8, 9.</note>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98029:5"/>and <hi>Oneſimus</hi> a beloved brother; to the end that the ſtate of the Apoſtle might bee made knowne unto them, and likewiſe their ſtate made known unto him: Thereby to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort their hearts, and to eſtabliſh them in the truth; herein compendiouſly ſetting before them a platforme both for life and doctrine; that ſo every Saint and faithful brother might know what belonged to his ſeverall vocation. And towards the end of his Epiſtle by way of conſolation remembreth the ſalutation of others of the holy brotherhood and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip as well as of himſelfe; as namely of <hi>Marcus, Ariſtarcus, Juſtus, Epaphras, &amp;c.</hi> So that <hi>Epaphras</hi> here mentioned is one of the beloved brethren, and fellow ſervants, whoſe ſalutations to the Church that was at <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> to the Saints and brethren there, the Apoſtle remembreth in this Epiſtle; as in the text, <hi>Epaphras</hi> who is one of, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In my judgement the Apoſtle is more zealous and affectionate in the ſalutations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred from <hi>Epaphras,</hi> then from any other of the brethren: Becauſe in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the ſalutations of <hi>Epaphras,</hi> he ſo highly commendeth <hi>Epaphras</hi> for his love, eſpecially toward the Coloſſians. This is obſerved by the ſeverall commendations of others here mentioned compared with the commendations which are given of <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras, Ariſtarcus, Marcus, Jeſus,</hi> which was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98029:5"/>called <hi>Juſtus,</hi> they were his fellow-workers unto the Kingdome of God; <hi>Luke</hi> a beloved Phyſician, theſe are commended in brieſe; but <hi>Epaphras</hi> hath a large commendation; two whole verſes are ſpent to this purpoſe (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make a ſhort epiſtle;) in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of <hi>Epaphras,</hi> which the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions here following ſhall more plainely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, to the end that the worth of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paphras</hi> for imitation may be had in ever laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remembrance. Wherefore obſerve (I beſeech you) firſt, who is here commended; <hi>Epaphras:</hi> and in him the matter of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation; that is why, and wherefore he is commended. Secondly, by whom hee is commended, and in him the manner of his commendation: I beare him record.</p>
            <p>The perſon commended is called <hi>Epaphras,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nomen quaſi not amen. etym.</note> I ſuppoſe it to be his name taken in baptiſme at his converſion from Paganiſme to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,<note place="margin">Coloſſe a town of <hi>Phry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia. Alſt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Tim. 1.6. Tit. 3.1. 1 Pet. 1.12, 13 Col. 1.7.</note> which might be done at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> (where <hi>Peter</hi> baptized Phrygians and others) not without ſignificancy, eſpecially in that he was after his converſion deputed to a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall calling: which calling requires that men be put in minde and remembrance of their duties by the miniſtry which was the practice of the Apoſtle toward <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> And of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to the diſperſed Brethren. And <hi>Epaphras,</hi> properly ſignifieth an admonitor, or one that putteth in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98029:6"/>and in this point he was for them a faithfull Miniſter of Chriſt, well brook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his name by his office: a fit name for a ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt; ſo that it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> to heare of <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras,</hi> and to have his name mentioned in the Epiſtle, whereby they received a teſtimony of his love toward them, requiting that te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of their love in the Spirit, which was declared by <hi>Epaphras</hi> unto the Apoſtle. <hi>Epaphras</hi> in thoſe dayes was glorious among the Saints on earth,<note place="margin">Col. 1.8.</note> but now is he glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous among the Saints in Heaven. And ſo in remembrance of the man wee come to the matter of his commendation; which is grounded on three ſeverall foundations, as they lye in order of the Text. Firſt, upon his love to his countrey, who is one of you, and for you. Secondly, upon his calling and office, a ſervant of Chriſt: Thirdly, upon his labour and exerciſe of prayer, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to his calling, and love to his countrey; alwayes labouring for your fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently in prayers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In which holy exerciſe of his there of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be conſidered the ſubject matter of his prayer, and the ſeverall cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances thereof: The ſubject matter of his prayer is, that they may ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God: The ſeverall circumſtances are theſe: Firſt, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98029:6"/>painefulneſſe of his exerciſe in prayer, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by labour and ſtriving; yea; and that fervently: It was not faint and eaſie, cold and perfunctory, but hot and fervent with labour and ſtrivings, for ſurely to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour fervently in prayer is a painefull and hot exerciſe; this is amplifyed by his zeale, for hee had a great zeale for them. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the continuance of his exerciſe in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Alwayes, that is, conſtantly and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, not intending every minute of every day, but exerciſe of prayer every day: As it was called a continuall burnt-offering which was offered but morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every day, <hi>Numb.</hi> 28.4. compared with verſe 6. So they may be ſaid to pray alwayes and continually, which morning and evening doe offer the ſpirituall ſacrifice of prayer. Thirdly, the extenſe of his laborious prayers, which are made not onely for the <hi>Coloſsians,</hi> but alſo for them of <hi>Daodicea</hi> and <hi>Hierapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> other congregations where <hi>Epaphras</hi> had beſtowed his labours to plant the grace of God in truth. Thus much concerning the grounds of his commendation in generall. Now with your leave (and liking as I hope) I ſhall a little more diſcourſe upon thoſe grounds of the Apoſtles commendation of <hi>Epaphras</hi> in their order; whereof the firſt is the ground of his juſt commendation taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his love to his country, who is one of you,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98029:7"/>labouring for you and hath a zeale for you, ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epaphras</hi> was a <hi>Coloſsian,</hi> their owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman and townſeman, their countryman either by birth, or by education, or by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, in which ſeverall ſenſes one may be ſaid to bee a countryman or townſman,<note place="margin">Natus in Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem, educatus in Nazareth, incola in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilact.</note> as Chriſt was a Bethlemite, a Nazarite, and a Capernaite: <hi>Lyra</hi> ſaith perhaps he was a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile by Nation, and made <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſciple; Without perhaps <hi>Dioniſius Carthuſianus</hi> ſaith, he was <hi>natione Coloſſenſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Forte crat Gent. lis natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; de par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus Coloſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium. Lyrain locum. Dionyſius Cart. in lbcum.</note> a countreyman of that place; this agreeth with the text, for he was one of them, <hi>Marcus, Ariſtarcus;</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> called <hi>Juſtus,</hi> they were Jewes, of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. but <hi>Epaphras</hi> was their owne countryman, and by that tye had a nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer relation unto them, which cauſeth him more fully to expreſſe his love and affection toward them. It was their glory that ſuch a flower grew in their garden, as <hi>Theophilact</hi> noteth upon the place, much more for their conſolation and comfort that they had ſuch a faithfull Miniſter, and ſuch a beloved bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Neſcio qua natale ſolum dulcedine cunctos</l>
               <l>Ducit, &amp; immemores non ſinit eſſe ſui.</l>
            </q>
            <p>He is unnaturall that hath no better affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his native ſoyle then to a forraine country;<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.</note> By the rivers of <hi>Babylon</hi> we ſate downe and wept when we remembred thee O
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98029:7"/>Sion: <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> could not be forgotten, rather the right hand ſhould forget her cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the tongue cleave to the roofe of the mouth; whom nature hath joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they cannot eaſily be put aſunder. This made <hi>Mordecai</hi> and <hi>Heſter</hi> to intercede for their Countrymen at <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> Court.<note place="margin">Heſter 4.</note> As it was ſayd of the couragious ſouldiers in <hi>Hectors</hi> army,
<q>Enreliqui cives veſtra virtute teguntur:</q> So it may be ſaid of good men well affected to their Country, that the endeavour and care of one man doth many times deliver a whole city from diſolation. Were the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Spartans</hi> by <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> accounted <hi>Moenia urbis,</hi> wals of the city? Certainely good men are <hi>Propugnacula accleſiae,</hi> the defence of the Church; like the Towen of <hi>David</hi> builded for an armory, whereon hang a thouſand Bucklers, all ſhields of mighty men.<note place="margin">Can. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>Sodome</hi> had beene delivered had there beene but a few righteous men in that place to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceded for the reſt, for good men borne and abiding in a towne or countrey, are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Auxiliatores ab ipſa natura ſuppeditati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> helps ordained by nature for that purpoſe; Therefore what ſome one may prize too much (as <hi>Lots</hi> Wife did her delightfull <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>) one cannot chooſe but look back upon, to wit, his owne country; the ſympathy of native affection is not eaſily wiped off, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98029:8"/>it appeareth by <hi>Moſes,</hi> into whoſe heart it came to viſit his brethren the Children of Iſraell,<note place="margin">As 7.23.</note> after 40. yeares ſpent in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court.
<q>
                  <l>O patriae natalis amor! Sic allicis omnes.</l>
                  <l>O quantum dulcoris habes!</l>
               </q> Such was the love of <hi>Epaphras</hi> to the <hi>Coloſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> the firſt ground of his commendation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ground of his worthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations is, that he was a ſervant of Chriſt, and ſo generally is every beleeving Chriſtian, bought and redeemed from the bondage of ſinne and Satan to ſerve and obey God in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.18.</note> For ſuch as are made free from ſinne doe become the ſervants of God, and therefore being delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from our enemies wee muſt ſerve him without feare in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe all the dayes of our life, and hereby ſuch as love the Lord Ieſus in ſincerity, are called and accounted (as our Saviour Chriſt was) his righteous ſervants,<note place="margin">Eſay 53.11.</note> or rather by this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they have obtained a greater honour then to be called ſervants,<note place="margin">Rem 12.1.</note> for we are no more his ſervants but his ſonnes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.7. Becauſe we doe and performe that reaſonable ſervice which belongeth rather unto ſons, then ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. Such ſervants were <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob; Job, Noah</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> and ſuch are all thoſe that deſire to glorifie God by doing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98029:8"/>his will with fervency of ſpirit ſerving the Lord.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.11.</note> Theſe are they which are numbred of the Tribes of Iſreal,<note place="margin">Revel. 7.</note> one hundred forty and four thouſands, and of all nations and kindreds and people and tongues, a great multitude, which no man could number, and are called the ſervants of our God, who are ſaid to bee ſealed in their foreheads, in that they doe openly profeſſe Chriſt, and embrace the truth, and make profeſſion thereof with courage and conſtancy; making an open ſhew of their faith,<note place="margin">Revel. 14.1.</note> becauſe the Name of the Lamb of God is written in their foreheads in this number. <hi>Epaphras</hi> was a ſervant of Chriſt in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall acception, and we which truely beleeve &amp; profeſſe Chriſt with him, are fellow-ſervants. Now there is alſo a ſervant of God or of Chriſt, ſpecially taken for one, that is a ſervant by an eſpeciall calling or function, wherein he is to doe God and Chriſt an eſpeciall ſervice: ſuch are they that ſerve faithfully in their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, being thereunto called,<note place="margin">Acts 13.2.</note> as <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> and that is chiefly to ſhew unto men the way of ſalvation; ſo teſtifiyed by the Damo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.17. Such ſervants were <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Iames,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Iude:</hi> ſo ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelves in the proemes of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Epiſtles. And the office of theſe ſervants was principally (like <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi>) with boldneſſe to ſpeake the Word of God;<note place="margin">Acts 4.13.</note> God
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98029:9"/>may juſtly chalenge ſervice from all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, becauſe he hath formed them, from all good Chriſtians, becauſe he hath redeemed them, but from his Miniſters principally, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath called them to be the chiefeſt of ſervants in their holy function; he ſaid to <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 44.21. 1 Cor. 6. ult.</note> thou art my ſervant, for I have formed thee; to the Iſrael of God, thou art my ſervant, for I have redeemed thee; to the faithfull Miniſter, thou art my ſervant, for I have called thee, or appointed thee to be a choſen veſſell to beare my Name before Gentiles and Kings,<note place="margin">Act. 19.15.</note> and the Children of Iſrael.<note place="margin">Mat. 20.1.</note> Theſe are ſhadowed by the hired ſervants which labour in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. In all theſe reſpects was <hi>Epaphras</hi> a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Chriſt, but eſpecially in his miniſtry; his labours for the Coloſſians doe manifeſt his faithfullſervice,<note place="margin">Col. 1.7.</note> for he was a faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt for them. Firſt, in that they had learned of him to know the grace of God in truth, having done his office faithfully in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpell;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.3.</note> a right Evangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſpeaking unto them to edifying, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation and comfort, and labouring for them by earneſt and fervent prayes,<note place="margin">In Text.</note> which are the maine duties of a faithfull Paſtor in relation to his flocke. When <hi>Epaphras</hi> was at Coloſſe, he was chiefly buſied about Gods errand, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering his mandates to the people. Now that, he is at Rome he is buſied about the Coloſſians
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98029:9"/>errand, to deliver petitions for them unto God. And this he doth with ſuch earneſtneſſe, that (like <hi>Iacob</hi>) he is wreſtling with the Angell,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.26.</note> he will not be anſwered untill he receive a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. <hi>Orandi arte capi Deus ſe patitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maldon. in Jo.</note> God is pleaſed ſo to be overcome, and no way elſe; for by this ſacred force the violent take the Kingdome of God, and if importunity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with the unrighteous,<note place="margin">Luke 18.5.</note> much more the righteous Iudge.</p>
            <p>The third ground of his deſerved commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is taken from the worke he undertooke and performed on the behalfe of his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the Coloſſians, his holy exerciſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; wherein to commend the worke I obſerved ſeverall circumſtances, and the ſubject matter of the ſame: the circumſtances are already handled, though briefly, and therein I referre you to that which hath beene formerly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. The ſubject matter is now the thing which I intend to treat of, wherein is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended all neceſſaries to make perfect and compleat Chriſtians. Hee prayeth for them that they may ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God; that is, (as I doe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it) that they may be perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in obedience to all the will of God. Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience makes the ſoule of man Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant; nay it makes the ſoule the wife of its Saviour. It is divinely ſpoken of a morall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98029:10"/>man,<note place="margin">Eſchyl.</note> that ſaid, <hi>Obedientia eſt foelicitatis mater, &amp; ſervator is Iovis uxor:</hi> That is, obedience is them other of happineſſe, and the wife of the ſaving God.<note place="margin">Gen. 22.28.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> had the promiſe, <hi>Quia obediſti voci mea,</hi> becauſe thou haſt obeyed my voyce; and for this grace hee had the honour to be called the Father of the Righteous: but our Saviour Chriſt did more by obedience for man, becauſe by his obedience wee are made righteous;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note> and of him it is ſaid that hee was <hi>factus obediens,</hi> as ordained of the Father for that purpoſe, and for this purpoſe alſo, that wee in him, and by him ſhould learne obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to all the will of God; and this was the <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> the deſired happineſſe which <hi>Epaphras</hi> prayeth for to betide the Coloſſians, that they might ſtand perfect and compleat in obedience to all the will of God. Hee will have them to be perfect and compleat; that is, to lacke nothing, to be abſolute and entire to be all full, without the leaſt defect, to have all excellency, even in the ſuperlative degree, ſo that there ſhould bee no want nor poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of adding any thing; he prayeth for their Chriſtian perfection, that they might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,<note place="margin">Mat. 5. ult.</note> as our Father which is in heaven is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: whereunto Chriſt exhorteth, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Chriſt propounded a paterne to all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers to be obedient to the will of God in all things;<note place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note> God is moſt abſolutely perfect in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98029:10"/>his Eſſence, in his Attributes, in his Workes. Of this perfection in God, Chriſtian perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on commeth ſhort, it is not ſo much as a point to that line, or as a drop to that Ocean; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe it is accepted of God, and accounted a perfection: Firſt, by comparing it to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the men in this world; and next, by their imitation and reſemblance which they have of God and his Sonne Chriſt in the workes of holineſſe; for ſuch as labour for Chriſtian perfection, they bewaile their own imperfections, and ſtrive by holy deſires and endeavours for a heavenly perfection, they exerciſe themſelves in holy duties, are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with God in the inward man, and are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly minded, they are patient in adverſity, forgiving injuries, praying for perſecutors, and are ready upon occaſion to helpe their greateſt adverſaries: they practiſe the rules of charity toward all men, exerciſing good workes, and carefully walking in their ſeverall callings. After this manner, and in this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a Chriſtian perfection may be had,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> by the helpe and aſſiſtance of that grace which is ſufficient for us. We have it in this life but in part, but when that which is perfect (indeed) is come,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.10.</note> then that which is in part ſhall be done away. And we muſt have patience to awaite untill we arrive to that harbour, where the ſpirits of juſt men are made perfect,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> to bee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98029:11"/>perfect indeed. Wherefore it becommeth every good Chriſtian to labour for ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as may be had in this life, thereby to fit himſelfe for reall and abſolute perfection in the life to come. <hi>Eſt aliquid prodire tenus.</hi> It is availeable to doe our endeavours: one may be as <hi>Neah</hi> was,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.9.</note> a perfect man in his generation; &amp; the mandate to <hi>Abraham</hi> is to all the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> 
               <hi>Walke before me and be thou perfect:</hi> for not onely the man of God in his holyfun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but alſo the ſervant of God in his holy converſation muſt bee perfect to every good work.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.</note> And for that the chiefeſt grace and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this life conſiſteth in love; the Apoſtle calleth love <hi>vinculum perfectionis,</hi> the bond of perfection. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.14. And wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> in the Canticles ſpeaking myſtically of the graces proper to the Church of Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>vna eſt columba mea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>perfecta mea,</hi> Which our tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rendreth, my Dove, mine undefiled is one, uniting love and perfection in every good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>This perfection is firſt in the heart, there rooted, &amp; thence ſpreadeth unto the tongue &amp; the hands. It is firſt in the minde and the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and thence proceedeth into words and workes by a ſanctified operation, for ſuch a perfection is required. Firſt, wee muſt ſerve God with a perfect heart, as the good King <hi>Ezechiah</hi> did,<note place="margin">2 King. 20.3.</note> and as <hi>David</hi> commanded
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98029:11"/>his ſonne <hi>Solomon</hi> to doe.<note place="margin">1 Chion. 28 9.</note> And then with our tongues, it any man offend not in word, the ſame is a perfect man. And for our hands,<note place="margin">James 3 2.</note> they are to be made perfect unto every good work.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.14, 15.</note> By this meanes preſſing hard toward the mark for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus. Let us therefore as many as bee perfect, and would be really perfect, bee thus minded. For this perfection and fulneſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured <hi>Epaphras</hi> on the behalfe of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen the Coloſſions, in his prayers, and farther limits this perfection and fulneſſe with the will of God. For his labour for them in prayers is, that they may ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God: where his will is to be underſtood, not for his Eſſentiall Attribute, which is the councell of his will,<note place="margin">Voluntas. Volitio. Volitum.</note> 
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11. for that is hidden from us; nor for his will bringing to paſſe what he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, for ſo his judgements are unſearchable, and his wayes paſt finding out, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. And who hath refiſted his will:<note place="margin">Rom. 9.19.</note> but for the object of his will, which is revealed and made manifeſt by the word taught and preacht. This is the will of God required to be done of us, in which will we muſt ſhew our obedience.<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>In the volume of the booke</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>it is written that I delight to doe thy will, O my God!</hi> which is Prophetically ſpoken of Chriſt, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorically of every good Chriſtian, whoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98029:12"/>duty it is to be a follower of Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.1.</note> For it is juſt and requiſite for ſuch as know the will of God, ſhould approve the things that are more excellent, as inſtructed out of the volume of his booke.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.18. Luke 6.46. Mat. 7.21.</note> Why ſhould we call him Lord and Maſter, if we doe not the things that hee ſaith: It is not every one that ſaith, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in heaven, ſaith our Saviour Chriſt. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that we be transformed by the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our mindes, that we may prove, and by our obedience approve,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> what is that good and acceptable, and perfect will of God. It muſt muſt be unto us as it was unto Chriſt, meat to doe the will of God, and to finiſh his worke, Ioh. 4.34.</p>
            <p>Mens thoughts ought eſpecially to pitch on three things concerning the will of God: Firſt, what he will doe with us. Secondly, what hee will doe for us: And thirdly, what hee will have us to doe. If we doe what hee will have us to doe, then will he make us veſſels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: this will he doe with us, and he will bleſſe us here and hereafter, this hee will doe for us. The ſumme of our obedience to the will of God in doing what he will have us to doe, is, Firſt,<note place="margin">Acts 17.10. John 3.16. 1 Theſſ 4.3.</note> to repent ſeriouſly: Secondly, to believe in Chriſt conſtantly: Thirdly, to lead a holy life continually. It is the will of God that wee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98029:12"/>recover our ſelves out of the ſnares of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.26.</note> and turne from ſinne unto God, and ſo make our ſelves new creatures, that wee may believe in Ieſus Chriſt, by faith appprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to bee our Prieſt to offer ſacrifice for us; our Prophet to teach, and our King to rule and governe us; and that we become holy, as he is holy, eſchewing evill and doing good,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.16.</note> ſeparating our ſelves from wickedneſſe, and wicked company, dedicating our ſelves and labours to God and godlineſſe, walking cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly, ever learning and practiſing piety, devotion, and heavenly mindedneſſe, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſelves from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, and perfecting holineſſe in the feare of God;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1.</note> forſaking our owne weake and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt wills, and applying our ſelves wholly to the will of God, which calleth us to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and newneſſe of life. For if God bee our Father, what Chriſt applied to the Scribes and Phariſees to another purpoſe, is moſt true of us, The workes of your Father yee will doe. To doe his workes, and obey his will,<note place="margin">John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.44.</note> confirmeth the ſpirituall kindred (farre more noble and excellent then the carnall) betwixt Chriſt and us: for whoſoever ſhall doe the will of his father which is in heaven,<note place="margin">Mat. 12, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> he is his brother, and fiſter, and mother:<note place="margin">Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.21.</note> and his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and brethren are thoſe which heare the word of God, and doe it. Where the word
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98029:13"/>of God, and the will of God are one, and of one ſignification, that no man might bee to ſeeke where to learne, or how to know the will of God.<note place="margin">Wilſon.</note> There need no rules of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, no decrees of Popes, no traditions of the Church, for the ſalvation of mens ſoules, or the ordering of mens lives;<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.17.</note> the Scripture alone (which is a moſt abſolute witneſſe of Gods will) is ſufficient to make the man of God perfect. There is the rule and Canon of obedience to the will of God; becauſe all do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines neceſſary thereunto, are in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures fully declared and expreſſed. For when <hi>Moſes</hi> had told the people the words of the Lord, and had taken the Booke of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and read it in the audience of the people, they ſaid: All that the Lord hath ſaid, we will doe, and be obedient, Exod. 24.7. And our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle thanketh God for the Romans, that they had obeyed from the heart that forme of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which was delivered them, Rom. 6.17. For to obey is better then ſacrifice;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22.</note> becauſe he that ſacrificeth, doth but ſlay a beaſt, but he that obeyeth, doth ſlay himſelfe in his owne corrupt will and naturally depraved affections. Now then <hi>Epaphras</hi> in the ſubject matter of his prayers for the Coloſſians, doth include the ſum of all perfection neceſſary to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in this life, in that he praieth, that they may ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98029:13"/>God. And here the Apoſtle doth not onely pray, that they may be perfect and complear, &amp;c. but alſo that they may ſtand perfect, &amp;c. where the Metaphor in the phraſe of ſtanding, is not to be omitted; becauſe to ſtand in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is to be conſtantly ſetled in the ſame, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying to abide and continue in it, and not to be drawne away from that ſtation and poſture by any aſſault or temptation: as the Romans are ſaid to ſtand in grace, Rom. 5.2. And as the Galatians were adviſed to ſtand faſt in their Chriſtian liberty, Gal. 5.1. And the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians are exhorted to take unto them the whole armour of God, that they may bee able to withſtand in the evill day; and having done all, to ſtand, Epheſ. 6.13. For as the counſell of the Lord is ſaid to be ſure and immutable;<note place="margin">Heb. 6.17.</note> ſo the Prophet David ſaith, It ſtandeth for ever.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 33.11.</note> 
               <hi>Epaphras</hi> prayeth not only for an <hi>habendum,</hi> but a <hi>tenendum</hi> to, that ſo the grace of obedience to all the will of God, may be theirs to have and to hold. And no marvell that <hi>Epaphras</hi> had ſuch a zeale for them; becauſe there was a poſſibility that they might be ſpoyled through Philoſophy and vain deceit,<note place="margin">Col. 2.8.</note> after the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt, which might bee feared; and therefore out of the earneſtneſſe of his zeale for them, he laboureth inſtantly with our Apoſtle to write this Epiſtle, and ſend faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98029:14"/>meſſengers with the ſame, as <hi>Tichious</hi> and <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> that as they had received Chriſt by the miniſtery of <hi>Epaphras,</hi> ſo they might walke in him by the counſell and conſolation of the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">Anxiè ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Pel. in loc.</note> To this purpoſe his zeale is ſhewen for the Coloſſians, in that hee was very earneſt and carefull for them, that they might conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the doctrine by him taught and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; whereby the foundations of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity layd, might not be thrown down or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned. As there is a zeale of God for men expreſſed by the zeale of the Lord of Hoaſts for the remnant of Iudah, and thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine of Ieruſalem, 2 King. 19.30.31. So there is a zeale of men for God, which was the zeale of <hi>Elias,</hi> being zealous for the Lord of Hoaſts; becauſe the children of Iſrael had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken his covenant, broken downe his Altars, and killed the Prophets, 1 King. 19.10. And there is againe a zeale of men for men: this was the zeale of <hi>Epaphras</hi> for the Coloſſians. The zeale of God for men is the abundant and earneſt, love of God for the good of his Church and his people. The zeale of men for God is the fervent and zealous love of men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God for the advancement of his glory. The zeale of men for men is the hot and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt affection that the Church and people of God have to doe good one to another. Zeale being ſtill taken in the better part for true war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98029:14"/>and religious zeale: for this zeale of men to men ſetteth forth the fruits of it ſelfe in mercy and compaſſion,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> in the deſires of doing good to all men, eſpecially to them of the houſhold of faith; in the hatred of prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the furthering of Gods true worſhip and ſervice, in wraſtling againſt the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world, ever hotly purſuing that grace of God which teacheth us to live godly,<note place="margin">Tit, 2.12.</note> &amp; righteouſly, &amp; ſoberly in this preſent world. The zeale of men for men, is poſitive; of men for God, is comparative: but that of God for men, is ſuperlative. This we may admire, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two we muſt practiſe. To be zealous as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paphras</hi> was; and withall, that our zeale be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive, not unto one perſon, or one place one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but unto many perſons, and many places, even unto all the world, and all perſons in the world. For looke how farre the commiſſion from God extendeth to goe and teach;<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19. 1 Tim. 2.4.</note> ſo farre it commandeth to extend the rayes of our love and affection; even to ſuch as are of Coloſſe, Laodicea and Hierapolis, the Cities and places which had no long exiſtence. For in <hi>Nero's</hi> time,<note place="margin">Strab. lib. 10.</note> (as Hiſtorians write) they all periſhed with an earth-quake. From ſuch deſolation the Lord deliver us. Nevertheleſſe, the love of <hi>Epaphras</hi> toward them is here highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; and where-ever this Epiſtle ſhall be read, what this <hi>Epaphras</hi> hath done for the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98029:15"/>ſhall be told for a memoriall of him. And ſo much for the perſon in my text com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and the grounds of his commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: It remaineth that I ſay ſomewhat of the perſon that commended him.</p>
            <p>The perſon that commended him (as I have ſaid before) was the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and the manner was by bearing record or giving teſtimony, of both which bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fly and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For the perſon commending, as he was not a Citizen of a meane City,<note place="margin">Acts 21.39.</note> ſo he was not a man of a meane quality, for he was a choſen veſſell unto the Lord,<note place="margin">Acts 9 15.</note> to beare his name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gentiles, and Kings, and the children of Iſrael; and by the Apoſtles, <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> he was appointed (I may ſay conſecrated) the Apoſtle or Biſhop of the Gentiles; he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no queſtion but his teſtimony would bee accepted of the Churches as it was at Rome,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.2.</note> where he witneſſed by his Epiſtle the zeale of Iſrael,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3.</note> at Corinth, where he witneſſed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution and liberality of the Macedonians, at Galatia,<note place="margin">Gal 4.15.</note> where hee witneſſed the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of their love toward him; and here at Coloſſe where he witneſſeth the zeale of <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras</hi> toward the Coloſſians. It was the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Epaphras</hi> to be limned by ſuch a Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">Tul. de or at.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> the Oratour eſteemed it ſufficient that wiſe <hi>Cato</hi> approved him, though others condemned him. And <hi>Pauls</hi> teſtimony of <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98029:15"/>was as much (if not more) as if all the other Apoſtles had borne record of his juſt commendations;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.40.</note> for the Apoſtles judgement as in other matters, ſo alſo in this, was guided by the Spirit of God. Undoubtedly <hi>Epaphras</hi> had never obtained theſe commendations from Saint <hi>Paul</hi> unleſſe hee had duly deſerved them, and the cauſall particle doth enforce it, for I beare him record. Wherefore to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by him, was the greateſt honour the times could afford, and that was juſtly due unto <hi>Epaphras.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proſp. de ſym.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> was another <hi>Simmachus mirabili eloquio &amp; ſapientia praeditus,</hi> wiſe and learned, <hi>vir totus exſapientia &amp; virtutibus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Boetius de eod.</note> full of grace and goodneſſe, which <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> ſaid of himſelfe, <hi>mei moris eſt bene cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitis approbatiſque, ferre ſuffragium, nec perſonas hominumſed vitae merita cogitare.</hi> My manner is to approve ſuch as are well knowne, and well deſerving, not reſpect mens perſons, but to weigh and conſider the merit of their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. There were but few to give ſuch teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Epaphras,</hi> and therefore for the future glory of <hi>Epaphras,</hi> the Apoſtle doth beare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, to make an everlaſting record of <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras</hi> his well deſerving. What was requiſite to a ſure teſtimony is found in the perſon of Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> Firſt, eminency in authority. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, approbation of fidelity. Thirdly, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary integrity. All theſe were in him, for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98029:16"/>he was conſpicuous and eminent in place and authority; one of an approved fidelity, and his life and converſation full of exemplary integrity;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.11.</note> for authority he was not one whit behinde the chiefeſt Apoſtles;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.12.</note> for fidelity, he was accounted faithfull, and ſo put into the miniſtery: For integrity, his converſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his converſation, his life made good his doctrine,<note place="margin">Gal. 2, 20.</note> for Chriſt lived in him. The integrity of his converſation was approved by the viper that fell from his hand, from the courteous entertainement that hee received from <hi>Iulius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 27. &amp; 28.</note> whoſe defence and patronage ſaved him when the mu inous Souldiers would have killed him, and from <hi>Publius</hi> and the Barbarians that thought him to be a God. But above all, how did the Diſciples at Caeſarea witneſſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the integrity of his life, when they not onely wept,<note place="margin">Acts 21.13.</note> but did even breake their hearts to forgoe him; ſo that it might be truely ſaid of this Apoſtle (in whom Chriſt lived) as it was ſaid of Chriſt himſelfe by the Centurion, certainely this was a righteous man.<note place="margin">Lake 23.42.</note> This was the applauſe and commendation which good men and wiſe men did ever ſtrive for. <hi>Laudari a laudato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cice. 4. Tuſc. qu.</note> to be well ſpoken of by them that were well ſpoken of: the approbation of one <hi>Paul</hi> was better then the praiſes of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand paraſites. This approbation had <hi>Epaphras</hi> from <hi>Paul;</hi> the Miniſter of the Coloſſians
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98029:16"/>from the Biſhop of the Gentiles; and it were to be wiſhed, that every Paſtor ſet over the Congregations in the Church of England, had the like approbation from his Dioceſan.</p>
            <p>In the application of the Text give me leave to commend unto you an <hi>Epaphras</hi> now living, whom we of this place have round zealous for us, and of whom I now beare record; Let us examine how and in what meaſure hee may be paralleld to the <hi>Epaphras</hi> of St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Epaphras</hi> had a relation unto the Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſo this man to us. <hi>Epaphras</hi> ſaluteth them by <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle; this man by his ſeverall Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles unto me for you, ſaluteth you. <hi>Epaphras</hi> was their Countrey-man, ſo this is ours. <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras</hi> was a ſervant of Chriſt, ſo is ours too; Firſt, in the common and generall ſervice of Chriſtianity: Secondly, in the ſervice of the Miniſtery in particular, though not by a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſervice and calling, to teach and preach the Goſpel of Chriſt in his own perſon; yet <hi>alique mode;</hi> for that he procureth Sermons to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at his coſt and expenſe; and this way doth exerciſe a miniſteriall function, though not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, yet efficiently, for the glory of God, and the good of this congregation. <hi>Epaphras</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them; this man is not behinde in the like holy exerciſe for us. Wherefore I deſire your patience to heare ſome paſſages, word for word as they are delivered in his ſalutations by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98029:17"/>ſeverall Epiſtles; In one Epiſtle it is thus: I aim at thoſe of my countrey by neereſt relation, &amp; them of the Pariſh and Towne wherein, I was born. And again, I cannot do leſſe then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the place of my birth, and the poore that be in that towne; and I deſire that my gift (viz. his benevolence and contribution) may ſtir up ſome to the like actions whilſt they live, and not defer it till their death. And againe, I moſt humbly pray you (writing to me your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) to give unto your Pariſhioners foure Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this yeare, and I pray God heartily, that they may worke upon the hearers effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, as they are by me intended for their good. And againe, I ceaſe not to pray to God for the increaſe of your talent, and that your miniſtery may diſtill upon the hearts of your hearers, to gaine ſome, and to direct, eſtabliſh and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort others to Gods glory, and your everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting peace and happineſſe. And againe, my prayer to God for you and yours, is, that hee will abundantly according to the riches of his grace, make your labours moſt profitable and glorious in your charge, and the high calling that God hath called you unto. And againe, I pray heartily unto God that I may bee what I am inſtructed in from men of your ranke and calling, who are the lights of the people, and the guides of ſoules, for whom my prayers to the God of Spirits (which is the quickning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98029:17"/>ſhall never ceaſe to be poured forth, that every one of you may be as <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> to go in &amp; out before your people, and to ſpeak a word in due ſeaſon to thoſe that hear you for their and your owne ſalvation: So to Gods gracious protection I commit you and them. And unto theſe his ſeveral prayers for me your miniſter, and you my Pariſhioners, his alms ſo liberally extended toward the poore of this place, and then tell me wherein he comes ſhort of <hi>Epaphras.</hi> There is not a Sabbath in the yeare, wherein his hand is not extended to our poore,<note place="margin">On the Feaſt of S. Luke, the Purification of the Virgin Mary, Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion day, and S. James, on each day allowing 10.5. to the poore, and 10.5. for a Sermon.</note> and at four feſtivals in the yeare plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully enlarged, not onely in Almes, but Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons alſo, that ſo the whole congregation may be fed, ſome ſpiritually, and ſome corporally by his pious bounty. S. <hi>Paul</hi> did teſtifie that <hi>Epaphras</hi> had a great zeale for the Coloſſians his countrey-men, and it was ſo; and I (though inferiour to the Apoſtle, yet witnes the truth) doe teſtifie of our friend, benefactor and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyman, that he hath a great zeal for you, and certainly it is ſo. Wherefore let us then in ſome thankfull way acknowledge the benefit of his love towards us,<note place="margin">Gal. 1. ult.</note> &amp; make requitall as the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Iudea did for S. <hi>Paul,</hi> even by the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of God in him, and let us all in generall pray for him as our Apoſtle did for the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of <hi>Oneſiphorus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord give mercy unto his houſe, for he hath oft refreſhed us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98029:18"/>
            <p>However, if you for your part bee negligent and backward, yet I for my part will ſay, and heartily pray, Peace be to him, and love, and faith from God the Father, and the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.23.24.</note> And grace bee with all them that love our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in ſincerity. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:98029:18"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Johaunes Hanſley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May 29. 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
